♪
[SITARA (ADULT)]
In the distant past,
scholars used geometry
to establish the size
and scope of Earth
for the first time.
In which case,
could one also use geometry
to determine the size and scope
of the fate we hold
in our very hands?
This is the story of a witch
who made a vast,
expansive continent
into her plaything.
♪
[Sitara pants]
[Ahmad groans]
[Muslim prayer call
in the distance]
[Ahmad gasps, grunts]
[Sitara
continues panting]
[Pigeons cooing]
[Sitara gasps]
[Muslim prayer call
continues]
[gasps]
[AHMAD] Where are you trying
to fly to, my little bird?
[exclaims]
You're quite a handful, child!
♪
[indistinct chatter]
I love the bazaar here.
It is so full of life.
Mistress, once your iddah
for the late master is over,
we'll go to the shops.
Yes, let's.
But today, I just hope
Allah will guide the way
and lead us
to find a fine slave.
-Uh?
-Not as fine as you, though.
[Fatima and Zumurrud laugh]
[indistinct chatter]
[FATIMA] Hmm...
Each one of them
is a hard worker.
[FATIMA] Hm.
This woman can cook up any meal
you desire,
for example.
-She's a great seamstress.
-Hm. Hm.
And this one here
has the gift of gab.
What a perfect
conversation partner, right?
Well, perhaps.
But what we need help
with the most right now is...
Is housecleaning.
That huge mansion
is just too much
for me to handle!
Indeed, and I still haven't
finished sorting
all my late husband's
belongings.
[AHMAD] Ah, say no more!
What do you think
about this woman, then?
There's no one can clean
the way she does!
Hello, my name is Anis!
Cleaning isn't about
what you feel like discarding,
but what you wish to keep!
Your days will be neat and tidy,
I give you my word!
That is wonderful!
How much would she be?
I'll let you have her
for 800 dirham.
[gasps] I know that slaves
are expensive, but my goodness.
Oh, please, Mr. Ahmad!
Isn't there any way
you could go lower?
[AHMAD] Mmm...
Normally, I would refuse
a request like that.
Just this one time, though.
I will let you have her
for only half price!
[Fatima and Zumurrud gasp]
But in return for this...
Come here.
[FATIMA AND ZUMURRUD] Huh?
[SITARA] Uh?
[AHMAD] Now go on.
Do as I taught you.
[Sitara chuckles]
Oh, how cute!
And who is she?
Her name's Sitara,
and I just acquired her.
Oh, your name's
meaning is "star."
-That's so lovely!
-[Sitara chuckles]
[Ahmad clears throat]
Although she may just be
a little bashful,
her smile is quite fetching,
as you can see!
And if she were given
a proper education,
I think she could be a servant
to someone of high standing!
So, here's what I'm proposing.
-Lady Fatima...
-[FATIMA] Uh?
Your household is known
for being rather scholarly,
and Young Master Muhammad's
perceptive mind
shines brightly
even here in Tus.
So, studying with you
will give her real cachet!
Might I trouble you to take her
into your home for a while?
[FATIMA AND ZUMURRUD] Huh?
-[UNCLE] What?
-[SITARA] Uh?
You agreed to this?
Oh, please.
You're the only one
who's truly qualified
to give her lessons now,
brother.
I'm still fulfilling my iddah,
and you're
the best teacher I know.
As you are aware,
whether you're a slave or not,
every Muslim's duty
is to seek knowledge.
I suppose.
[Sitara chuckles]
Recitation's the cornerstone
of learning.
And the first step
on that journey
is to recite the Quran
properly.
So now I want you
to repeat after me.
[SITARA] Hm?
"In the mighty name of Allah,
the Most Gracious,
and also the Most Merciful."
Uh? Now it is your turn.
[SITARA] Hmm?
[UNCLE] Hmm? Well, go on.
Your turn.
[Sitara chuckles]
♪
[bird chirping]
It's hopeless.
No matter how hard I try,
she sits and smiles,
showing absolutely no interest
in learning at all.
But I swore I'd take her in.
[Sitara chuckles]
You can keep the other slave.
I'll repay the discount.
I hope you'll forgive me,
brother.
[Uncle sighs]
-[SITARA] Hmm?
-I'll have him come get you.
-Just wait here, all right?
-[SITARA] Hm. Hm.
[UNCLE] No, I'll go.
Mr. Ahmad's establishment, yes?
[FATIMA] Yes. I'm so sorry.
[SITARA]
Here's my chance!
If I don't leave, who knows
where I'll get sold off to?
I need to go home!
♪
[man grunts]
[Sitara gasps]
[Zumurrud humming]
Find her?
[ZUMURRUD] Mm-mm.
[Uncle sighs]
[Sitara gasps]
I'm so lost!
How do I get out of here?
[SITARA]
Can't let him see me.
[Sitara gasps]
And Young Master Muhammad's
perceptive mind
shines brightly
even here in Tus.
[MUHAMMAD] Uh?
[SITARA] Excuse me.
Uh, where is the door?
Hey! This is most improper!
Don't you know that
a woman must not ever reveal
her uncovered hair to a man?
[chuckles] It's all right,
'cause I'm still little!
You're too close.
And besides, it looks to me
like you're still a child, too,
Young Master Muhammad!
So, um, who are you?
-My name is-- [gasps]
-[ZUMURRUD] Ah-ha!
Since you up and disappeared,
I've been looking
all over the place for you!
Mm. The roses were so pretty,
I had to see them!
Actually, she was looking
for the way out.
[Sitara grunts]
Unbelievable!
How could you try to escape?
Now, now there.
In only a few moments,
my brother will be back here
with Mr. Ahmad.
I'm sorry.
Didn't you want to go back?
No, not back
to that man's place.
To the house where
my mother and I used to live.
Soon after she died,
her master sold me off
to the highest bidder.
-[Fatima gasps]
-Then that isn't your house,
so there's no point!
Remember, you're a slave!
If you want a real home
worth returning to,
study hard, so you'll be bought
by a good master!
No! I don't ever want to study!
And I won't be making
cute faces anymore, either,
because it only makes me seem
more valuable to them!
[cries] If I learn,
I'll just be sold again
and taken away forever.
I'm sick of going places
where I don't recognize things!
[cries]
[MUHAMMAD] Little girl.
I mean, Sitara,
is that the reason
you came here to study?
[SITARA] Uh?
Even though our lots in life
might seem fairly different...
Say, Zumurrud?
Will you go and fetch me
a water bucket from the kitchen?
A large one please.
[ZUMURRUD] Yes, of course.
[MUHAMMAD]
Come with me.
[SITARA] Huh?
Where are we going?
[Muhammad chuckles]
Up here?
Will this one here be all right?
Mm-hmm. Thanks so much.
I'll be dropping it
in the courtyard.
[BOTH] Huh?
[Muhammad grunting]
Young master, why?
Do you really think
the girl is a lost cause?
-[loud clang]
-[both yelp]
[AHMAD] What on Earth was that?
Oh, my goodness!
What's going on?
[BOTH] Huh?
[UNCLE] Is everyone all right?
What was that?
Wait... Did lightning strike
the house?
Are... are you sure
those barbarous nomads
haven't started attacking us?
[whimpers]
[Uncle gasps]
-[Muhammad laughs]
-[UNCLE] A water bucket?
Everyone down there
was so afraid.
Young Master, your little prank
went too far!
Just out of curiosity,
why are you two
so calm and composed?
Well, why wouldn't we be?
We knew you were
about to drop it,
and both of us covered our ears.
So what you're telling me is,
you both predicted
a future in which
there would be a loud noise,
then you took some precautions.
That about right?
Well, yes. I suppose so.
Then, just maybe
that's what
learning's all about.
[Sitara gasps softly]
[MUHAMMAD]
At the moment,
you don't have
any idea where you are,
what's happening here,
or what is to become of you.
It's all so unknown.
My uncles
and the ones down there
are in a similar situation.
But if one were to study
and become wise,
then one would know
the best course of action,
no matter what the situation
might be. Always.
And that could never be
a bad thing.
Is that learning?
-Uncle! I'm sorry about that!
-[ALL] Huh?
It was me!
[ANIS] Oh, this water bucket
is all bent now
and won't stack anymore!
How awful!
[ZUMURRUD] You can go
and have it repaired.
I'll make sure
all the cooking is done.
Ah! Hello there!
[SITARA] Mm?
If you ever have any questions,
feel free to ask me.
[SITARA] I will.
[SITARA (ADULT)]
With a new perspective.
Sitara remained
and found herself serving
in a scholarly household.
[Fatima humming]
[Sitara gasp excitedly]
You're looking really beautiful,
Mistress!
Oh, thank you!
Although, I feel rather
self-conscious.
Now don't you be silly!
It's your first day going back
to the hammam after your iddah!
So, go have some fun.
Put on a little makeup,
dye your hair
and hands with henna,
and start chatting up a storm
with all the other wives there!
Very well.
I'll bring you with me someday.
Sitara.
Great!
"And to Allah belongs
all that is in the heavens,
and all that is in the Earth."
My recitation is still different
than Uncle's somehow.
I should have him
teach me again.
[MUHAMMAD]
Mother, can we talk?
[yelps] Uh, where is she?
[SITARA] Mistress Fatima
left for the hammam
a little while ago.
I thought she told you.
She did?
I forgot that was today.
Does this mean you only have
enough room up there
for your studies?
As I have told you before,
please don't leave your room
with your hair uncovered.
And as I've told you,
I'm still a little girl!
Besides, you're still only 12,
Young Master Muhammad.
What's so bad about somebody
who can't grow a beard
setting foot in a girl's room?
I am not a child!
[Sitara laughs]
Am I immature in your eyes
as well?
[SITARA] Huh?
[Muhammad sighs]
[MUHAMMAD]
My teacher said I'm too ignorant
in the ways of the world.
[SITARA] Do you mean
the one who teaches law?
[MUHAMMAD]
Yes, Ustad Kamal al-Din,
whom Father introduced me to
before he died.
But recently though,
I've sensed that we both have
very different views.
He doesn't even give
clear answers
to certain questions
I pose to him.
You have
far too little experience
to truly comprehend such things.
That's why I'm leaving here
on a journey.
[Sitara gasps]
I want to travel to Nishapur
and visit its renowned teachers.
But eventually, I'll explore
many other cities as well,
and engage with wisdom
from any and all sources...
Searching for truth!
My father was a scholar,
and I believe that's the path
he wanted for me.
[Sitara exhales]
How wonderful!
Well, I have some washing to do,
so I need to go.
Sure.
[SITARA]
"And to Allah belongs
all that is in the heavens
and all that is in the Earth."
It seems like no matter
how hard I study,
I'll never be able
to match Master Muhammad.
[rooster crows]
♪
Farewell, Mother.
I'm leaving now.
To not bring shame
upon your dear father,
devote yourself to your studies.
I will.
Take good care of yourself.
[sniffles]
As-salamu alaykum.
[in English]
I will see you partway there.
Thank you for all this, Uncle.
[gasps softly]
Hold on.
Girl...
[SITARA] Hmm?
So, I've been told
that you still can't read.
No.
-Well, then...
-Uh?
-I will be writing you letters.
-[gasps]
So when I become a teacher,
I'll know how to convey
my lessons
to young children like you.
And I'll write as simply
as I can.
-That good?
-I'm practice?
There is one thing I ask of you.
Please study and read them
to Mother.
Do you understand, Sitara?
[Sitara gasps]
No matter what, don't ever
stop learning, all right?
I won't. I promise.
And now I'm off.
[SITARA (ADULT)] Muhammad,
a boy hailing from Tus,
who would become
a renowned scholar.
And Sitara,
a little slave girl...
This would be
the very last time
they ever saw each other
face to face.
-[hooves clopping]
-[horse snorts]
[SITARA] "In the name of Allah,
the Most Gracious,
the Most Merciful."
Uh?
[ZUMURRUD] It's the Tus militia.
Ms. Zumurrud?
I bet they're on their way
to go scouting outside the city.
From what I've been told,
armed nomads have been
appearing in the area.
My brother is down there
with them, somewhere.
Though, I haven't seen him
in ages.
[SITARA] Huh?
Mikhail and I were born
in a distant land
far to the west.
Right on the sea!
And when the sun set,
it turned everything
into a lovely purple!
[SITARA] Really?
We were both poor,
but I still loved
watching the sea!
-[FATIMA] Sitara?
-[SITARA] Uh?
Could I trouble you
to read this letter?
Yes! Of course!
In the usual room, right?
My goodness!
Look at how happy she is!
[Fatima laughs]
All right. So,
"Mom, Uncle,
In these past eight years,
I've studied many fields
of learning,
including philosophy,
medicine, and astronomy.
[MUHAMMAD]
Nishapur is a sprawling,
vibrant city where
many noted scholars gather.
For example, I was instructed
by Farid al-Din Damad
in the medical arts founded
by Ibn Sina.
Unlike theology,
in which one simply parrots
what one is taught,
science is knowledge
that's built upon
real-world experiences.
[BOTH] I'm finding
this way of learning
is far more agreeable.
And also...
[chuckles]
...if our little star, Sitara,
would be open
to learning about them,
please see that she studies
the various postulates
and theorems
of Euclid and Ptolemy."
-Uh?
-[both chuckle]
Come along with me.
[Sitara exclaims]
Can't believe you're showing me
all of these precious books.
-Thanks!
-Of course.
It's a duty upon each Muslim
to continue seeking knowledge.
That's what my late
scholar husband had told me.
"Euclid's Elements"
is that one right there.
Great!
[grunts]
It says, "A point is that
which has no part."
And that "a line
is breadthless length."
Therefore, "The ends
of a line are points."
It's like he's just stating
obvious things
in a really complicated way.
[FATIMA] But why do
obvious things seem so obvious?
It's through amassing examples
one by one
that we prove
universal principles. [chuckles]
Still with me?
I'm sorry,
but I don't see how I'm supposed
to apply any of this knowledge.
Well then, let's find
a more interesting one for you.
Al-Biruni. Here's his book
on astrology.
Astrology, huh?
[FATIMA] This should be better.
-Now, look at this.
-[gasps]
"The diameter of the Earth
is 2,163 and one-third farsakh,
and its circumference
is 6,800 farsakh."
Do you mean he traveled
to the ends of the Earth?
Oh, no, that would be
quite impossible.
By forming a right triangle
using a spot on the ground,
a mountaintop,
and the center of the Earth,
it's then possible to determine
the Earth's radius.
A mountaintop, huh?
[FATIMA] There's yet
another method of calculating
the Earth's circumference
using the angle of shadows
on the ground.
[SITARA] Just with shadows?
[bucket clangs]
[Sitara gasps]
[FATIMA] All of these
were derived
from the universal knowledge
that's found in Elements.
Well? Is your interest piqued?
[Sitara gasps softly]
-[gasps] It's burning!
-[Sitara yelps]
[exclaims]
[chuckles nervously]
It is one problem after another
with you lately.
I hope you'll forgive me,
Ms. Anis.
Now listen, Sitara.
There are slaves
who do all sorts of jobs.
There are even those who acquire
all kinds of knowledge
to entertain their masters.
And depending on the case,
some are promised their freedom.
That said,
you should never get
your hopes up too high.
Because we are in no position
to decide such things.
We're property, not people.
-[UNCLE] Listen, girls.
-[BOTH] Huh?
Gather 'round, please.
Could you also fetch Zumurrud?
Is there something wrong?
Our militia fought,
but the nomads have won!
♪
[SITARA (ADULT)] Heaven didn't
answer our prayers with mercy.
They were met only with fire.
Instead of rain,
embers fell across the land,
followed by silence...
which took place of the flames.
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA (ADULT)] Next episode:
"The Roses that Bloom in Safar."